in this video we're going to talk about
the law of conservation of
mass so what is the main idea behind
this
law the main idea is that matter cannot
be created or destroyed in a chemical
reaction so let me give you an example
let's say if we react methane gas with
oxygen so let's say if we have a closed
container and we're going to make 16 G
of Meth
in this
container we're also going to place 64 G
of oxygen
gas so the methane and the oxygen gas
they cannot leave the container they're
stuck
there now as the reaction proceeds it's
a combustion reaction it's going to
produce carbon dioxide and water
vapor depending on the
temperature now let's say if if you
collect 44 G of carbon dioxide according
to the law of conservation of mass how
many G of water should you expect to be
present at the end of this
reaction now think of the total mass of
the reactants the reactants are the
stuff on the left
side we have 16 G of methane and 64 G of
oxygen so therefore we're starting with
80 g
of
reactants so before the reaction we had
80 g of matter at the end of the
reaction according to the law of
conservation of mass in a closed system
you should still have 80 g of mass so if
we have 44 G of carbon dioxide the
remaining amount of mass should be water
80 - 44 is
36 so therefore we should back to
collect 36 G of water and that's the
main idea behind the law of conservation
of mass if you have 80 g of material
inside the closed container before the
reaction then when the reaction is
complete you should still have 80 g of
matter inside that container in a
chemical reaction the only thing that's
happening is that the atoms are
rearranging themselves here carbon is
bonded to hydrogen but now it's Bond
oxygen so therefore the total mass
should remain the same the atoms are
simply switching Partners they just
rearrange themselves in this chemical
reaction but the amount of mass the
quantity of matter should still remain
the same the only way you can change it
is if you add more mass into the the
chamber or the reaction
container for